If you are currently taking trading
advice from me on WhatsApp or Telegram,
you are being scammed by someone
impersonating me. If I've emailed you
from a Gmail address to give you trading
advice, you are again being scammed by
someone impersonating me. If you found
your new financial adviser in the
comments section of one of my videos and
they are earning you huge profits
trading crypto and stocks, you are being
scammed. It does not seem to be possible
to make these scammers go away. So, I'm
going to tell you what their scams look
like so that you can avoid them. I'm Ben
Felix, chief investment officer at PWL
Capital, and I'm going to tell you how
to not get scammed.
[Music]
Online investment scams are no joke.
Canadian Anti- Fraud Center data show
that $310 million were reported lost to
investment fraud in 2024. But they also
estimate that 90 to 95% of fraud goes
unreported. So the real numbers are
likely much larger. As the Canadian
Securities Administrators suggest,
successful disruption of fraud requires
intelligence that sheds light on the
means and methods employed by criminals,
which is exactly what I'm going to do in
this video. I think this is important
because education about the specifics of
how scams work reduces their
effectiveness. In a 2014 study,
consumers at a high risk of being
scammed were educated about one of two
different scams. The consumer later
received a staged scam phone call. Those
who had been warned about the specific
scam that was later pitched to them were
much less likely to respond to the scam
than consumers who were forewarned about
a different scam. Though education about
either scam did have a positive impact.
Scammers are not very nice, but they're
also not idiots. They use techniques
that leverage human emotions to build
trust and they exploit points of
weakness in their victims. I suspect
that one of the reasons scammers are
impersonating me is a technique called
source credibility, where scammers take
advantage of the fact that people are
more likely to believe others in
positions of authority and to trust
organizations that they perceive as
legitimate. By posing as me, the
scammers are able to leverage my
asynchronous relationship with my
audience to build trust, making it
easier for them to perpetrate their
scam. They also use social proof. We see
this in the YouTube comments example
that I'll describe later. They create
the perception that lots of people have
had a great experience with a fake
financial adviser. Scammers also play on
common behavioral biases like optimism
bias where people overestimate the
probability of good outcomes and
underestimate bad ones. The halo effect
where people quickly trust someone based
on a positive first impression. Present
bias, where people tend to maximize
short-term pleasure, like the potential
for a big investment gain without fully
considering the potential consequences.
Regret aversion, where people worry
about missing out on something like a
big investment opportunity. And
representativeness, where people
extrapolate general conclusions from
specific data points, like the recent
returns of an individual stock. Let me
just say that I like you guys. I
appreciate you watching my videos, but
it is extremely unlikely that I will
contact you unless you're a client of
PWL Capital, and even then it would be
rare. PWL has teams of financial
planners and portfolio managers that
deal directly with clients, but I am not
one of them. I'm the CIO. If I do reach
out to you, it will be from my PWL email
address, and it will not be to give you
trading advice or to tell you to sign up
for a shady investment platform. Okay?
There are three main scams that I've
come across related to my YouTube
content. Investment group scams, email
impersonation scams, and fake financial
advisor pig butchering scams. Investment
group scams are typically conducted on
encrypted chat platforms like Telegram
and WhatsApp. I am not on Telegram. If
you are in a Telegram group or otherwise
communicating with me on Telegram, you
are talking to a scammer. These groups
are posted online and often run by
accounts using the name and profile
picture of someone credible. They
promise to include you in a community
focused on trading stocks or crypto
based on rigorous research and that you
will earn high returns by following the
advice. I was sent a link to one of
these WhatsApp groups which I joined and
I was contacted by one of the admins.
They were using my name and my picture
to communicate with other people. The
group had 90 people in it when I joined.
It is wild stuff. I chatted with a
scammer for a bit while they were
impersonating me and they didn't know I
was me and eventually I was picked on
buying a specific stock. The scam here
seems to be to encourage people to buy
small illlquid stocks to pump up their
price so that the scammers can sell
their holdings of the same stock at an
inflated value causing the price to then
decline. The scammer makes a profit at
the expense of the person taking their
trading advice. It's a classic pump and
dump with a modern group chat twist. The
person I chatted with was very smooth.
They had a Toronto phone number, used my
name and picture, they wrote
articulately, and if I did not know any
better, they might have seemed credible.
They even offered up the PWL Capital
website when asked where they work. I
would hope that this goes without
saying, but it clearly needs to be said.
Nobody has the ability to consistently
identify stocks that will have high
returns in the future. Trading
individual stocks is extremely risky and
anyone confident in their ability to
generate high returns from stock trading
should be a big red flag, especially if
they want to share those high returns
with you. The rare talent that is able
to profit consistently in financial
markets is not on WhatsApp or Telegram
sending their trading strategies to
internet strangers. Email impersonation
scams involve sending emails to people
while posing as someone else. In my
example, someone posing as me was
reaching out to people who had commented
on my YouTube videos. The scammer said
they were emailing to thank the viewer
for their engagement on my YouTube
channel and inviting them to chat.
Listen, again, I do appreciate all of
you, but I will probably never send you
an email. And again, if I do, it will
not be from a Gmail address. Someone did
reply to the scammer and they sent me
the follow-up from the scammer. They had
offered to share a comprehensive
walkthrough including actionable steps,
key insights from the latest research
and some of the most promising
investment opportunities with strong
potential for returns. This has all the
hallmarks of a scam. It seems likely
that it's another pump and dump, but I
never followed up on this one because
the email address being used was
reported to Google and shut down. These
scams are all bad, but the one that
drives me crazy is the YouTube comment
section fake financial advisor pig
butchering scam. This thing is the bane
of my existence because they will not go
away no matter how many times I report
and ban the accounts posting these
comments on my channel. They've also
gotten better with AI as the comments
are starting to be tailored to the
content of the video. So, they're harder
to detect as scams, but they do
generally still follow a predictable
format. Most commonly, it starts with a
generic comment, often with someone
referencing their own success in
achieving a specific dollar amount with
their investments. I'm guessing there's
some psychology behind that since they
all seem to do it. For example, this
video really hit home for me. Retirement
has been such a rewarding chapter of my
life. My wife and I worked hard to get
here and we're incredibly thankful for
where we are today. Now we're debtree
with a net worth over $3 million and
that investment income supports us every
week. This comment is on my video about
the historical comparison of renting
versus owning in Canada. So, it's not
really relevant at all to the content in
this case, but it might make you wonder
how this person was so financially
successful. This is where their
financial advisor comes in. It's always
a very specific full name. Links are
typically caught in YouTube comment spam
filters, so the scammers won't post
links. Instead, they post the first,
middle, and last name of their supposed
advisor. Searching that full name online
brings you to a somewhat
professionallook website listing things
like credentials, testimonials, awards,
and licenses. Most of this information
is of course fake, but similar to the
other two scams, they will often use the
name of an actual registered investment
professional so that the name shows up
in a registration search through
securities regulator websites. They will
even often link out to these legitimate
websites to make themselves look more
credible. It's very sneaky. This is
problematic because one of the best
things that you can do to verify whether
someone offering you investment advice
is legitimate is look them up on a
regulatory website. In Canada, we have
are they registered.ca where you can
search for the registration of anyone
registered with securities regulators in
Canada. In the case of this fraudulent
adviser and my WhatsApp impersonator,
this step may not help. What I would say
though is that a professional financial
adviser will probably not communicate
with you through WhatsApp, Telegram, or
an email address that is not associated
with their registered firm. If in doubt,
call the firm that they are registered
with at the number listed on their
registration record to verify any
suspicious communications. Out of
curiosity, I did contact one of these
fake financial adviserss through the
email address provided on their
fraudulent website. Don't worry, I used
a throwaway email address from a privacy
focused email provider. They asked me if
I've ever worked with a financial
adviser before, what active trading
accounts I have, my annual income,
whether I'm an aggressive or reserved
investor, the purpose of investment, and
my investment budget. Once I replied
with that information, they told me that
they're taking on their next batch of
clients in Q2 2025, and that I could
join that batch to begin investing and
earning. The pitch is that they are a
multimarket broker that trades across
three different markets while majoring
in digital currencies. When I said I was
interested, they sent me a PDF detailing
their offering. Again, don't worry, I
did not download the PDF. PDFs can
contain malicious code, so caution is
warranted here. The PDF I received is
incredible. It's like a master class and
what to look out for in an investment
scam. It contains huge amounts of
financial That is an academic
term defined in the 2022 paper
individual differences in susceptibility
to financial It is defined as
seemingly impressive verbal financial
assertions that are presented as true
and meaningful but are actually
meaningless. For example, from the PDF,
the quidd proquo strategy functions
through a simple economic law of
substitute goods where if goods A and
goods B are substitutes, a decrease in
demand of goods A will result to an
increase in demand for goods B.
Similarly, taking into consideration the
stock market and digital currency market
are both substitutes as they offer
similar services in the financial
market, the economic law of substitutes
will equally apply. Those words mean
absolutely nothing, but they could sound
smart and they're accompanied by
pictures of stocks going up. It seems
ridiculous, but I think this type of
text does act as a filter where people
without the financial knowledge to
realize that it's are prime
candidates for being scammed. This
document also includes another classic
scam attribute, the promise of
guaranteed profit with no risk. Most
investors want to earn high returns and
are concerned about losing money. The
reality in financial markets is that if
you want the expectation of earning
higher returns, you need to be willing
to take more risk. Diversification can
mitigate the risk of total loss, but
even a broadly diversified equity index
fund can go through double-digit
percentage point drops from time to
time, and it may take years to recover.
That is the reality of investing in
risky assets. But humans find losses
painful. Lots of overpriced and
otherwise suboptimal financial products
prey on this concern by promising
investors downside protection. In this
case, the scam adviser is offering a
guaranteed monthly profit of between 5
and 10% depending on the amount of
investment capital and whether you
choose a passive or aggressive
investment approach. Let's take a moment
with that information. If we take the
lower end, 5% per month, that is an
annual return of 80%. For context, the
most successful hedge fund in history,
the Renaissance Technologies Medallion
Fund, which has been closed at outside
investors since 1993, has an annualized
historical return of around 66% before
fees and 40% after fees. It is, of
course, implausible that Daisy on
YouTube just happens to have found
something better and is willing to tell
you about it. Actual guaranteed returns
available through guaranteed investment
certificates in Canada or certificates
of deposit in the US are much lower.
Canadian banks are currently offering
guaranteed rates in the 3 to 4% range
depending on how long you lock your
money up. Other than the guaranteed 80%
returns, the other big red flag here is
the claim that there is no downside
risk. The PDF says that the broker has
an alternative insurance that covers for
any losses incurred while trading for a
client should the profit realized in a
month fall below the agreed percentage.
This insurance will also make up the
deficit. That is not a real thing.
There's nobody taking the other side of
that trade. The PDF finishes with a list
of benefits that reminds me of that
scene from Step Brothers where they
pitch prestige worldwide. Retirement,
mortgages, crowdfunding, investment
advising, tax avoidance, college funds.
For the record, tax avoidance is not
something a credible financial adviser
will offer. Tax minimization stems from
good tax and financial planning, but tax
avoidance is inconsistent with the
overall spirit of the law. Anyway, I was
of course interested in signing up for
these 80% returns. So, I asked for the
next step. I was sent another PDF
requesting a ton of personal information
and was told to sign up for three
trading platforms. Two of them were
legitimate. One of them was clearly, to
my eyes at least, fraudulent. It was
explained to me that the adviser would
be copy trading in my accounts. I
stopped here because I did not actually
want to get scammed. But the next step
would have been for me to add funds to
the trading accounts, allow my new
financial adviser to trade in them,
acrue the appearance of large profits in
the fraudulent account, and then be told
to add more funds, likely with a promise
that doing so would increase my returns.
This would continue until I decided to
withdraw my funds, at which point I
would realize that I had been scammed.
At that point, it would be too late.
This is called a pig butchering scam.
They build trust, convince you that
you're earning large profits, get you to
add more funds, and then finally take
you to slaughter. Scams are
unfortunately part of life. They have
been around forever, and they're not
going anywhere. One of the best defenses
against scams is knowledge of scams. If
you know what scammers are trying to do,
you will be able to avoid getting sucked
into their traps. Unfortunately, the
people who most need to hear this
information will probably never watch
this video. To address this, one of the
relatively recent regulatory innovations
in Canada designed to help stop scams is
the trusted contact person or TCP.
Licensed portfolio managers and
investment advisers in Canada are
required to ask their clients to name a
trusted contact person. That is a person
that the client authorizes to be contact
if the adviser is concerned that the
client is being financially exploited
among a few other reasons. If you or a
close family member have a financial
adviser and have not named a trusted
contact person, I definitely think it's
worth doing. Thanks for watching. I'm
the real Ben Felix, chief investment
officer at PWL Capital. If you found
this information useful, please share it
with someone who may be at risk of being
scammed.